This שיעור shiur is דף כה, Daf Chaf-He, 25, and we pick
up with the תולש לאו היינו גוזז. Tolash Lav Hainu Gozez. The
line starts with the word יד, Yad, we're a good degree ahead,
we're like 10, 12 lines down. Let me summarize about what we
did yesterday and make one or two points. The משנה Mishna spoke
about tearing off hair in order to do שחיטה Shechita from בכור,
Bechor, but there's a פסוק Pasuk that you can't shear בכור, Bechor,
לא תגז בכור שורך. Lo Tagoz Bechor Shorecha. So the
question was why it's allowed, and the גמרא Gemara suggests one of
two reasons. One is because אינו מתכוין. Eino Mitkaven. Now really what
we would like to say about אינו מתכוין, Eino Mitkaven, it's going
to sound a little bit like that in the גמרא Gemara later,
doesn't mean that it happened accidentally, it means more like what we
would say about שבת Shabbos of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, Melacha She'eina
Tzricha L'gufa, meaning you're not really trying to pull out the hair
because you care about the hair, you're just trying to get it
out because you want to clear the space so you could do
the שחיטה Shechita or check for the wound.
That's really not אינו מתכוין, Eino Mitkaven, that's more like a שבת
Shabbos concept of you're not interested in it for the same purpose,
which is really not a concept by other areas. So רב אשי
Rav Ashi תוספות Tosfos was supposed to explain that אינו מתכוין Eino
Mitkaven means, although it's not clear from the גמרא, Gemara, means that
you actually are just trying to move the hair and when the
משנה Mishna says you pulled it out it means if it gets
pulled out but not intended. That's one way to explain the משנה.
Mishna. And the other way to explain the משנה Mishna is
that גוזז, Gozez, shearing, is a particular act. It means a shaver,
it means a, what do you call it, clippers, whatever it means,
it doesn't mean pulling out individual hairs, something you do with your
hand and you do in a localized spot. So that's not considered
גוזז. Gozez. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says: תולש לאו היינו
גוזז. Tolash Lav Hainu Gozez.
That's why you see קופיץ, Kupitz, by the way, so that means
I
was thinking about that too, קופיץ Kupitz could mean that yes it's
a blade but it's not a blade that would define it as
shearing, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't say it that way. That's true,
that is correct, I thought that too. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
asks which of these is correct. תוספות Tosfos asks isn't the obvious
נפקא מינא Nafka Mina whether you can do it intentionally or not,
but the גמרא Gemara and he has a whole discussion, but the
גמרא's Gemara simple explanation applies it to the question about whether you
can do it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why is it different
on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Because there was an אינו מתכוין Eino
Mitkaven issue that's a relevant fact by יום טוב Yom Tov as
well, that would make it allowed. But if it is defining it
as not גוזז, Gozez, well by שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom
Tov we don't define categories that narrowly. It's not just cooking, it's
not just baking, it's everything that's sort of related to using heat
to prepare food. So similarly it's not just גוזז, Gozez, plucking would
also be included and that would not be an exception. So the
גמרא Gemara said, well רב Rav said it does apply to יום
טוב, Yom Tov, but not for the reason we said, because רב
Rav personally holds אינו מתכוין Eino Mitkaven is a problem. So according
to רב, Rav, the only reason so that can't be the explanation
of אינו מתכוין. Eino Mitkaven. So rather let's read again what the
answer was for רב, Rav, so it said actually a line before
I just said,
לעולם סבר רב דהוה שאינו מתכוין. Le'olam Savar Rav De'ava She'eino Mitkaven.
Really רב Rav holds that something that you're not intending is אסור,
assur, forbidden. So that can't be the explanation of the משנה Mishna
and it can't be the explanation of why it's allowed on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. ותולש לאו היינו גוזז. Ve'tolash Lav Hainu Gozez. Here's
the explanation of the משנה Mishna because תולש Tolash with a hand
is not considered the same act as shearing. Fine, that explains בכור,
Bechor, that explains the משנה. Mishna. It doesn't explain why it's allowed
on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב, Yom Tov, let's say יום טוב,
Yom Tov, יום טוב Yom Tov because you're trying to שחט shecht
is why this specific question was יום טוב, Yom Tov, can you
do the same thing to שחט shecht on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
It doesn't explain that because by יום טוב Yom Tov the category
is not so narrow, it's a broader category and any type of
like removing hair is included. So the גמרא Gemara says, here's the
reason why it's okay on יום טוב: Yom Tov: וביום טוב היינו
טעמא דשרי דהוה ליה עוקר דבר מגידולו כלאחר יד. U'veyom Tov Hainu
Ta'ama De'shari De'hava Lei Okeir Davar Migidulo K'lo'achar Yad.
It's not just that it's not גוזז. Gozez. You're right, if something
weren't cooking but it was frying or baking, then you'd still be
חייב. chayav. But even within this different thing that you're doing, you
have to do it in a normal way. So we're not just
saying that using your hand isn't גוזז, Gozez, we're saying it's a
bizarre way for anybody who's trying to remove wool. It's כלאחר יד.
K'lo'achar Yad. So it's again, the example to use my cooking example
is, if I fry rather than cook, you're still going to tell
me I'm חייב, chayav, okay, but if I turn on the fire
with my toes and I flip my pancakes with, you know, holding
the frying pan with my toes, so that is not just that
it's not narrowly defined as frying, it's I'm doing it in a
strange way, כלאחר יד, K'lo'achar Yad, and that's why I'm exempt. So
different reason. It's certainly enough for our משנה Mishna just to say
it's not גוזז, Gozez, but for יום טוב Yom Tov purposes you
would also say that you are doing it in a strange way
and it's כלאחר יד. K'lo'achar Yad. Now a quick look at a
תוספות Tosfos for an interesting application, and also brings in the מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה Melacha She'eina Tzricha L'gufa question. תוספות Tosfos says דהוה
ליה עוקר דבר מגידולו כלאחר יד. De'hava Lei Okeir Davar Migidulo K'lo'achar
Yad. It's the second תוספות Tosfos here. He says אין ללמוד מכאן
שמותר לתלוש נוצה מצואר של עוף כדי לשחוט ביום טוב. Ein Lilmod
Mikan She'mutar Litlosh Notza Mitzavar Shel Of Kedei Lishchot Beyom Tov. Now
when תוספות Tosfos says אין ללמוד מכאן, Ein Lilmod Mikan, he's really
talking about a practical case. Okay, can we apply this גמרא Gemara
to say when we שחט shecht chickens on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
so that's interesting, right, they were still שחט shechting fresh chickens and
before the age of refrigeration you'd want to שחט shecht things fresh
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, can we שחט shecht chickens on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, can we pluck their feathers before we do the
שחיטה, Shechita, right, very analogous case? So if you can pluck the
wool from a sheep before your שחיטה, Shechita, how about plucking plucking
feathers? But there's an obvious difference, because why do we say plucking
the wool from the sheep's neck was okay? Because of because of
כלאחר יד, ke'lochar yad, as you don't normally remove wool by plucking
it. But how would you normally remove feathers? By plucking it. So
תוספות Tosafot says to says to okay well we'll talk about that
in a minute. So תוספות Tosafot says why דשרי הכא משום שינוי
deshari hacha mishum shinui
and anyway if you just skip a little bit
he says בנוצה benotza the second line ולא הוי כלאחר יד. velo
havei ke'lochar yad. So what's in this answer that it's according to
the answer אינו מתכוין eino miskaven you're מתכוין. miskaven. According to the
answer it's כלאחר יד ke'lochar yad by feathers it's not כלאחר יד.
ke'lochar yad. Now he asks another question which I just want to
read because also it's sort of the implicit issue that's going on
here as well. And then he says like this ואף על גב
דאין צריך ve'af al gav de'ein tzarich the line starts with אין
צריך ein tzarich כאן נוצה kan notza you really don't care about
the feathers והוי מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה ve'havei melacha she'eina tzricha legufa
right?
So it's like you're doing the מלאכה melacha of removing feathers,
removing you know sheep wool from a sheep, but you're not interested
in the product. And normal גוזז gozez is what you want to
benefit from the product. So why isn't it also the issue of
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha she'eina tzricha legufa? So what he's basically
saying is is that if we allow you to do כלאחר יד
ke'lochar yad in order to do removing the feathers to do שחיטה,
shechitah, why can't we allow you anyway it's also a דרבנן. derabbanan.
You're not interested in the product and if you're not interested in
the product it's not for the purpose of the מלאכה, melacha, that
should also allow it. So תוספות Tosafot says no אין למדין מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה מכלאחר יד. ein lemedin melacha she'eina tzricha legufa mike'lochar
yad. You can't compare the דרבנן derabbanan categories. Why not? So this
is generally an interesting question. I know I'm digressing a little for
הלכות שבת hilchot Shabbat but that's what we're about. But this is
interesting because even when something gets knocked down to a דרבנן, derabbanan,
there are different degrees of a דרבנן. derabbanan. When you do something
כלאחר יד ke'lochar yad with a שינוי, shinui, then you know it
is it's not easy to confuse it with the דאורייתא. de'oraita. First
of all visually and experientially it's different. I'm using my elbow, I'm
not you know I'm not doing it in the normal way. And
also well I would say not just visually but I would say
that when you do something in a strange way you're also sending
yourself a signal right that there's a problem here and I have
to do things differently. When you do מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa visually and experientially it's the exact same, right? You're
plucking feathers from the neck just like you would pluck it during
the week if you were interested in the feathers. The only thing
that's different is what's going on in your head. So that is
a lot closer, they're both close to the דאורייתא, de'oraita, it's one
step away from the דאורייתא. de'oraita. But מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa is even closer. So therefore although we allow כלאחר
יד ke'lochar yad for שחטing shecht on יום טוב Yom Tov to
get the feathers removed, we don't allow מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa. The other reason I wanted to read what?
Not feathers, you mean for the sorry the wool.
We would not allow for the feathers because that's not כלאחר יד
ke'lochar yad and מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. The
other reason I wanted to bring this up is because it raises
the general question which תוספות Tosafot doesn't address of why we're not
bringing up מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa here in
all these cases, right? Because the case about pulling the wool from
the sheep on יום טוב Yom Tov is not just a כלאחר
יד, ke'lochar yad, it's also a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa. You're also not interested in the wool. So I just
wanted to mention that, I don't really have a great answer, but
that is like the missing conversation from this גמרא, Gemara, right? What
about the fact that you're not really it's not a classic shearing
whether for whether for בכור bechor or whether for יום טוב Yom
Tov because you're not interested in the product. Okay, so that's the
question that is an issue that תוספות Tosafot raises, but it's interesting
that it's not raised in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a
look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this ותולש vetolesh line starting with the word ותולש. vetolesh. ותולש vetolesh
אמרי amrei that's we read that. Line starting with the word יד.
yad. ותולש לאו היינו גוזז? vetolesh lav hainu gozez? Are you telling
me that תולש tolesh is not the same as גוזז? gozez? Because
that's how we're explaining our משנה mishnah by בכור. bechor. והתניא vehatanya
we
learned in the ברייתא. braita. התולש את הכנף והקוטם והמורט חייב שלש
חטאות. hatolesh et hakanaf vehakotem vehamoret chayav shalosh chataot. So you pluck
a feather from a goose or from a chicken whatever let's just
say a goose and you want to use it as a quill,
okay? And you did this on שבת. Shabbat. Now, so you plucked
it, you were קוטם kotem you cut off the you know clipped
it at the head, and מורט moret and you you know used
your knife to smooth it and to sharpen and to make it
into a point. Okay, so you made a quill on שבת. Shabbat.
How many sins did you do? חייב שלש חטאות chayav shalosh chataot
three sin offerings, you violated שבת Shabbat three times. ואמר ריש לקיש
ve'amar Reish Lakish what are the three times? תולש חייב משום גוזז
tolesh chayav mishum gozez plucking the feather is גוזז gozez it's a
type of a
shearing, right? Because you're removing it and here you actually do want
the product, you want the feather. קוטם חייב משום מחתך kotem chayav
mishum mechatech clipping off the head is cutting, cutting is exactly what
cutting when is cutting מלאכה melacha on שבת Shabbat is not exactly
clear but it certainly is cutting I mean whatever not it's clear
but it's not being discussed here, but not all sort of tearing
stuff certainly if you tear open packaging is not cutting, but certainly
a cutting that is sort of done in a very particular way
because you want something a particular size and you're making something sort
of as a result that's certainly is a type of cutting. So
that's a cutting that is forbidden on שבת. Shabbat. וממרט חייב umemaret
chayav and when you sort of when you whittle it or you
know when you sort of smooth the tip... removing the feathers with
your knife and pointing making it into a point, that's חייב משום
ממרח chayav mishum memarei'ach because of smoothing. Okay, so that's also an
issue about sort of smoothing something over that comes from the making
of leather and that smoothing out the leather, but it applies to
any type of like smoothing that is done to, you know, create
something productive. It's an interesting question that comes up about
brushing teeth on שבת. Shabbos. You know, some people say you can't
use toothpaste because it's ממרח, memarei'ach, smoothing the toothpaste over your teeth.
But to me always seemed extreme bizarre. First of all, you don't
really care if it's I mean, I guess you don't want it
bumpy, but your point is just to get it all over, not
to actually, you know, smooth it as an act of smoothing. And
actually and you're not trying to create a smoothed product. Normally smoothing
is you're trying to get a smooth product, here you're just trying
to apply it. So I'm not giving a פסק psak about brushing
teeth on שבת, Shabbos, I just I just always thought that that
was a bizarre application. Anyway, when we learn מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos
we'll talk about that. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says you see
that you're חייב משום גוזז, chayav mishum gozez, okay, by the way,
here's the point, shh, here's the point that it's not כלאחר יד
k'le'achar yad as well because it's a bird feather. Okay, but anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says don't you see you're חייב משום גוזז? chayav
mishum gozez? How could you say in our משנה, Mishnah, Michael I'll
get you in a minute, how could you say in our משנה
Mishnah that it's not about גוזז? gozez? So the גמרא Gemara says
as Michael is obviously muttering under his breath, the גמרא Gemara says
שאני כנף דהיינו אורחיה. shani knaf dehaynu orchayei. Okay, a feather is
different, it's the normal way, which means not only is it not
כלאחר יד, k'le'achar yad, but also what is an act of shearing?
If I said what's an act of shearing by a sheep, you'd
get out your clippers. What's an act of shearing by a by
a goose? You get out a plucker or you use your hand.
So what is even defined as the act? Not just the normal
way of doing it. If I were to use my use my
shears for a goose or pluck with my hand from the sheep,
I wouldn't say I did it in a strange way, I would
say that's not called shearing. Okay, so sometimes like as I said,
when you do things differently it changes the definition, sometimes it's just
a bizarre way, and here the גמרא Gemara actually says, yeah, you're
right, when you use your hands for a sheep it's not just
כלאחר יד, k'le'achar yad, it's also not even גוזז. gozez. When you
use it for a goose, it's actually it's it's not כלאחר יד
k'le'achar yad and it is גוזז. gozez.
You use a shear for a goose, you use a shear for
a goose and that would be כלאחר יד k'le'achar yad probably, and
if you use your hands for the sheep, that would be but
more than כלאחר יד, k'le'achar yad, it probably wouldn't even be defined
as the act itself. The thing is for שבת Shabbos and יום
טוב Yom Tov it doesn't have to be the narrowly defined act
of גוזז. gozez. For
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov the key question is is
it normal way to do it or not normal way to do
it?
By by our משנה, Mishnah, by בכור, Bechor, the question is is
it defined as the act of גוזז? gozez? Okay, so did you
have a question, Dov? No? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומר סבר רבי יוסי
בן המשולם, U'mar savar Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam, since רב Rav holds
like רבי יוסי בן המשולם, Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam, he פסקן paskened
like רבי יוסי בן המשולם, Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam, but רב Rav
personally held דבר שאינו מתכוין אסור. davar she'eino miskavein assur. So how
does he understand רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam in
our משנה? Mishnah? Because he said using your hands is not גוזז.
gozez. So if that's what רב Rav is saying and he's saying
that I hold by the משנה Mishnah of רבי יוסי בן המשולם
Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam in the following way, understanding רבי יוסי בן
המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam to be saying that it's not גוזז,
gozez, so presumably at least according to
רב, Rav, רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam סבר ליה
כרב. savar lei k'Rav. So רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben
HaMeshullam also agrees with רב, Rav, meaning if you're explaining Rabbi Yosei,
how can he rule like רבי יוסי בן המשולם? Rabbi Yosei ben
HaMeshullam? Because he understands that רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben
HaMeshullam is not about אינו מתכוין, eino miskavein, if that's what he
was about רב Rav couldn't rule that way because רב Rav holds
the opposite. So he understands רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben
HaMeshullam agrees with him that דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino miskavein is
a problem and the only reason it's okay in the משנה Mishnah
is because it's not called גוזז. gozez. So that's according to רב's
Rav take, רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam agrees with
him that דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino miskavein is a problem. So
now we're going to challenge that. וסבר רבי יוסי בן המשולם דבר
שאינו מתכוין אסור? V'savar Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam davar she'eino miskavein assur?
Does he really hold that דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino miskavein is
forbidden? Now, if you would think there's one תנא tanna who it's
hard to prove what he holds on any randomly chosen topic, it
would be רבי יוסי בן המשולם, Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam, like who
ever even heard of him before? But now we are going to
prove that he does not hold דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino miskavein
is a problem. Let's take a look. והתניא, V'hatanya, we taught in
the תוספתא Tosefta in פרה. Parah.
Let's see if we knew פרה Parah we would have known it.
שתי שערות עיקרן מאדים וראשן משחיר. Shtei se'arot ikaran ma'adim v'rashan mashchir.
You have two hairs of a פרה אדומה parah adumah which are
not all right, if they're two black hairs it's not a פרה
אדומה. parah adumah. But let's say the hairs are not all black.
They're red at the tip or and black at the bottom or
the opposite, black at the bottom and red at the tip. So
because they're not all black, you're allowed to cut them away and
pretend they weren't there. That's pretty funny, isn't that? What what but
but
that's a good question. You're right, I mean if that doesn't totally
puzzle what's this middle thing? Presumably while they're there you can't call
it, you know, אדומה תמימה, adumah temimah, but because it's not but
because somehow it doesn't redefine its identity as a non-פרה אדומה, parah
adumah, so you once you remove them you're okay. Okay, so רבי
יוסי בן המשולם אומר, Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam omer, גוזז במספרים ואינו
חושש. gozez b'misparayim v'eino choshesh. Yeah, cut them away with the scissors
and you don't have to worry about it. What would you worry
about? You'd worry about גיזה בקדשים, gizah b'kodashim, because although the תורה
Torah explicitly not to do גיזה בקדשים, gizah b'kodashim, we learn that
it's prohibited by all קדשים. kodashim. He says don't worry about it.
Now the גמרא Gemara says so what does that mean don't worry
about it? So the גמרא Gemara says so why? So presumably the
גמרא Gemara is saying is because it's אינו מתכוין. eino mitkaven. And
presumably אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven רבי יוסי בן משולם Rabbi Yosi ben
Meshullam doesn't have a problem with it. Now the problem here or
the issue there is that אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven here does not
mean אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven because you are intending to cut them
away and you are using your scissors. That would, right, you need
to remove them. Okay, so the point of אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven
here is you don't care about the product and that's a type
of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzricha legufa, which is
normally a שבת Shabbos or a יום טוב Yom Tov issue, not
a normal, you know, איסור issur problem. But that is and that
actually is a better explains the גמרא's Gemara use of אינו מתכוין
eino mitkaven in the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah sounds like it's
intentional. So it actually sounds from this גמרא Gemara that when it
uses the phrase אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven it actually means to say
even if you are intending to do the act, since you don't
care about the removing of the hair per se, but actually it's
legitimate. In the משנה Mishnah you didn't care about the removing the
hair, you just needed the space. Here you care about removing the
hair but you're not interested in the product. That that is enough
to define it as not an act of גיזה giza and to
define it as permissible. So it's not that it happened accidentally, but
that your interest in it is not the classic act of what
גיזה giza is about.
Yes, so what makes it קדש kodesh if it's still not black
hair?
Well, you sanctified it as a פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
Right, so it's קדשים בעל מום kodshim ba'al mum or something exactly.
So a black hair would be a מום. mum.
That's I don't know if we would don't really define it as
a מום, mum, it would be analogous. We define it as like
it's not a אדומה, adumah, you know. But but that's would be
an interesting question if you are מקדיש makdish it for a פרה
אדומה parah adumah and it already had the black hairs and you
didn't notice them, right, so would it sort of follow the הלכה
halacha of like קדשים kodshim that a מום mum preceded, right, because
here particularly it's not even אדומה adumah and you were מקדיש makdish
it on the כוונה kavana that it should be a פרה אדומה.
parah adumah. It's like what if you're מקדיש makdish an animal for
an עולה olah and then you realize that it was a נקבה,
nekeivah, you know, maybe it's the same thing. Anyway, we're going to
see in a minute that it's not exactly קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban,
but that's where the גמרא's Gemara going to get into. רבי יוסי
בן משולם, Rabbi Yosi ben Meshullam, oh that is such a good
question, I don't know. You want to know if he lived in
the time of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, like why he's talking
about פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Yeah, I don't know. I mean, but
you've got you could look through all of מסכת פרה, Maseches Parah,
I mean I think that there's a lot of תנאים Tannaim there
that didn't live when there was. Yeah, yeah, I don't know. Charlie's
going to find out for us. Yes.
Does it make a difference, you know, assuming this is a sheep,
but let's say it's like a בכור bechor of a cow, right?
I mean you shear sheep, you don't like shear cows, right? So
like would the whole discussion be different if this was...
Well, the גמרא's Gemara that's a very good point. So the גמרא's
Gemara going to get to that. Okay, now I should just say
that because of this issue of אינו מתכוין, eino mitkaven, רש"י Rashi
basically says what I just said, that אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven means
you're not interested in the hair, you're only interested in fixing the
cow, which is essentially it's a fascinating point, it's essentially bringing the
concept of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa into other
categories. But that fits well with also the משנה Mishnah that we
were dealing with. תוספות Tosafos tries to pull it somehow back into
classic אינו מתכוין. eino mitkaven. Okay, says no, we're talking about not
those two hairs, we're talking about what happens if you accidentally cut
other hairs in the process. Anyway, the simple sense here is that
it's using אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven to mean you're intending to do
the act but not for the problematic purpose. So let's take a
look. Don't you see that he says דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino
mitkaven is okay? So the גמרא Gemara says no, there's a different
reason going on there. Let's take a look. שאני פרה דלאו
בת גיזה היא. Shani parah delav bas giza hi. Yeah, just like
Michael said. You don't normally you don't shear cows. So therefore the
prohibition of shearing קדשים kodshim doesn't apply to cows. Who shears cows?
It's not even relevant, it's not an act of shearing. So it
says one minute, והתניא, ve'ha tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
לא תעבוד בבכור שורך ולא תגוז בבכור צאנך. lo ta'avod bivchor shorecha
velo sagoz bivchor tzonecha.
Don't work the your you know the firstborn of your of your
cows and don't shear the firstborn of your sheep. ואין לי אלא
שור בעבודה וצאן בגיזה. Ve'ein li ela shor ba'avoda vetzon begiza. I
only know that you cannot work your ox that's a בכור bechor
or shear your sheep. מניין ליתן את אמור של זה בזה ואמור
של זה בזה? Minayin litein es amur shel zeh bezeh ve'amur shel
zeh bezeh? How do you know to apply the prohibitions across the
categories? תלמוד לומר לא תעבוד ולא תגוז. Talmud lomar lo ta'avod velo
sagoz. The ו, vav, don't work and don't shear, says that you
can't do the that act with the other animal either. So you
see there that you're not allowed to shear a בכור bechor that
is a cow and therefore you would not be allowed to shear
קדשים kodshim that is a cow. So why does he allow it
unless based on אינו מתכוין? eino mitkaven? So the גמרא Gemara says,
where are we, אלא שאני פרה דקדשי בדק הבית היא. ella shani
parah dekodshei bedek habayis hi. Oh, פרה's parah different, it's not a
real קרבן. korban. Now קדשי בדק הבית, kodshei bedek habayis, right, is
a it's not really בדק הבית. bedek habayis. Classic בדק הבית bedek
habayis is is where it's something is going to be used to
fix up the temple, right, for like you know so it's a
temple general operating funds, operating that maybe is קרבנות, korbanos, but anyway
it's like it's the building fund of the temple. That's קדשי בדק
הבית. kodshei bedek habayis. That's not what you're doing with this פרה
אדומה, parah adumah, but it's the category the גמרא Gemara puts it
in because this פרה parah is very strange. You שחט shecht it,
you sprinkle the blood towards the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it has
very קרבן... korban... qualities to it, but it's outside the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. And we can't have a real קרבן korban.
*Korban* being done outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, so the גמרא
Gemara's *Gemara* understands that the קדושה *kedusha* of the פרה אדומה *Para
Adumah* is like בדק הבית *Bedek HaBayit*, means it has קדושה *kedusha*
and it's שייך *shayach* to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, but not
a קדושה *kedusha* of a קרבן korban *Korban*. Okay, so therefore, the
prohibition of shearing and working is only by things that are קרבנות
*Korbanos* and the פרה *Para* is not a, is not a קרבן
korban *Korban*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והאמר רבי אלעזר *Veha'amar
Rabbi Elazar* קדשי בדק הבית אסורים בגיזה ועבודה be-gizah va-avodah. *Kodshei Bedek
HaBayit asurim begizah va'avodah*, but Rabbi Elazar says even if it's only
sanctified for the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, we had that earlier this
מסכת *maseches*, you cannot shear it and work it. מדרבנן *Miderabbanan*, okay,
that's only a rabbinic concern. So, you know, we're trying to get,
salvage the פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* here and that was only a
rabbinic concern. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* somehow doesn't buy that. ואיכא
איסור דרבנן *Ve'ika issur derabbanan*? So what? So since when can you
transgress דרבנן *derabbanan*, which is quite interesting, like they won't say that
they waived it in order to allow you to get a פרה
אדומה *Para Adumah*? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא ela
שאני פרה דלא שכיחא *Ella shani parah delo shechicha*. פרה אדומה's *Para
Adumah's* different or maybe it could also mean this particular case of
a פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* that has two hairs that can be
salvaged because they're not all black and can be sheared, that is
a very rare case. And therefore, the Rabbis did not intend their
restriction and their prohibition to extend to such an unlikely case. And
therefore, and particularly also there's a reason to allow it. So therefore
it says, therefore rather than saying we override it for the sake
of פרה אדומה *Para Adumah*, we say that the restriction was never
meant to include such a case. The way we answer it is
it's not based on אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven *eino miskaven*, it's based
on the fact that it doesn't have קדושת קרבן korban. *kedushas korban*,
and because it doesn't have קדושת קרבן korban. *kedushas korban*, therefore,
and because it doesn't have קדושת קרבן *kedushas korban*, therefore there's only
a rabbinic problem of shearing it which is not a problem here
because it is a special case. Yes, Charlie, you had a question?
Yeah, why didn't they just say that
rabbinic prohibitions in general don't apply to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*
when they're outside?
Oh, that's a first of all this isn't the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash*, as we said, but second of all that's an interesting point
and what is the scope of saying that אין שבות במקדש *ein
shvut bamikdash*? More has to do with like
the עבודה *avodah* that the כהנים *kohanim* are doing like as they're
actually bringing קרבנות *korbanos* as opposed to here which is much more
sort of preparatory. But in general the question of how big is
that scope of אין שבות במקדש *ein shvut bamikdash*, it's not as
categorical.
But yes, I just found out actually that Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam
was a sixth-generation תנא *Tanna* at the end of the second century,
so that would
and he seconded, so that's a good hundred years after the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* was destroyed.
No, I was going to say that like you know שבות במקדש
*shvut bamikdash* is sort of like שבת *Shabbat*, you're not actually burning
it on this פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* שבת *Shabbat* anyways, I mean
it's in the zone.
Right. Okay, so right, okay, so let's see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues, it says
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says וליחל וליפק לחולין וליגזיה *Veleichel velifok
lechullin veligzeih*? So which is now no longer a question of אינו
מתכוין eino mitkaven. *eino miskaven*, but whatever allowed you to do it
or maybe it is because maybe it fundamentally wasn't problematic at its
fine. But if you're still working around a דרבנן *derabbanan* or trying
to limit a דרבנן *derabbanan*, there's another solution. Why not redeem the
קדושה *kedusha*, וליחל *veleichel* meaning being מחלל *mechalel*, transfer the קדושה *kedusha*
of a פרה *parah* because it's not a קרבן *korban*. Since it's
not a קרבן *korban* you can transfer it without a מום mum
*mum*. וליפק לחולין *Velifok lechullin* and it'll go out to be non-sanctified,
וליגזיה *veligzeih* and then you'll shear it, והדר ליקדשיה *vehadar leikadsheih* and
then you'll re-give it the קדושה *kedusha*. Remove the קדושה *kedusha*, do
what you need to do and reinstate the קדושה *kedusha*. What's the
big deal?
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says דמי יקרין *Demei yakrin*. No,
it's very, very expensive. So find somebody that has ten thousand dollars
available for me to do the פדיון *pidyon* on. It's not so
easy to get that money and therefore it's hard to do the
פדיון *pidyon*. וליעבד כדשמואל *Velya'avad kedishmuel*? I want to do like שמואל
*Shmuel* says. דאמר שמואל *De'amar Shmuel* because שמואל *Shmuel* says הקדש שוה
מנה שחיללו על שוה פרוטה מחולל *Hekdesh shaveh maneh shechilelo al shaveh
perutah mechulal*. That if you transfer הקדש *hekdesh* even worth ten thousand
dollars on a dollar, it still works. Okay, even though it's not
an equal exchange. So why not do that here as well? So
wait a minute, אימר דאמר שמואל שחיללו *Eima de'amar Shmuel shechilelo*. שמואל
*Shmuel* says if you did it, it worked. לכתחילה lechatchila מי אמר
*L'chatchilah mi amar*? לכתחילה lechatchila, *L'chatchilah* you need to do it with
equal value and therefore it's hard to get together that amount of
money and therefore we're not going to remove the קדושה *kedusha*. That's
one answer. It is, it's not an אינו מתכוין *eino miskaven* and
otherwise it would work. It is, it's not an אינו מתכוין *eino
miskaven* but we're allowing it because it's only דרבנן *derabbanan* because of
special circumstances. איבעית אימא *Iba'it eima* and if you want you could
say רב סבר לה כרבי יוסי בן המשולם *Rav savar lah k'Rabbi
Yossi ben HaMeshulam*. רב *Rav* is פוסק *paskening* like רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi בן המשולם *Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam* and he's reading רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi בן המשולם *Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam* his way, that it's
about גיזה giza *gizah* not being, about plucking not being defined as
גיזה giza *gizah*. ורבי יוסי בן המשולם לא lo, סבר לה כרב
*Verabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam lo savar lah k'Rav*. That's not the real
פשט pshat *pshat* in רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi בן המשולם *Rabbi Yossi
ben HaMeshulam*. You understand what it says רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi בן
המשולם לא lo, סבר לה כרב *Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam lo savar
lah k'Rav*? It means it's not פשט peshat, *pshat* in רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi בן המשולם *Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam*. רבי יוסי בן המשולם
*Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam* actually holds אינו מתכוין *eino miskaven* is okay.
And since we see from the case of the
פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* that you don't care about the hair, you
care about just you know, getting it off of the animal. And
that since he holds אינו מתכוין *eino miskaven* is okay there, clearly
it's what he holds in our משנה mishna *mishnah* as well when
he says that you can remove the hair in order to do
the שחיטה shechita *shechita*. So that's פשט peshat *pshat* in the משנה
mishna. *mishnah*. רב *Rav* is פוסק *paskening* like him but not based
on his reasoning. רב *Rav* says real... because רב *Rav* holds that
אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* is a problem. So he's פוסק *paskening* like
רבי יוסי בן המשולם *Rabbi Yose ben HaMeshulam* for different reasons, that
the plucking is not defined as גיזה *geizah*. רבי יוסי בן המשולם
*Rabbi Yose ben HaMeshulam* himself says that אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* is
what motivates him and therefore by the way I'll repeat what I
said before based on רש"י Rashi *Rashi* which is the פשט *pshat*
and not תוספות *Tosfos*, אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* does not here mean
that it happened accidentally. The same way אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* by
the פרה *parah* means you're intentionally plucking it out but you're not
interested in the result and therefore it's not defined as גיזה *geizah*,
presumably a type of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melachah she'eino tzerichah
legufah* idea that presumably is also what would be meant by the
אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* of the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. We don't have
to read the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* that it accidentally fell out and
you were just trying to push it out of the way. The
point is you could be doing it intentionally but it's a type
of an אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* which means it's not an act
of גיזה *geizah*.
Okay so now plucking here we're trimming, right? What? We're plucking hair
words...
No you are plucking. What in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*?
No, no in the פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* you're clipping
the, clipping the wool, yes.
Yeah, you're not plucking.
You are plucking. But it's still an אינו מכוון *eino miskaven*, that's
exactly the point, that it's not about the plucking, it's about the
אינו מכוון *eino miskaven*. So we have two basic explanations of the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. One is an אינו מכוון *eino miskaven* which could
mean in the most classic case it happened accidentally and you didn't
intend it, or it could mean as we're seeing that it happened
intentionally but you weren't caring for the result. And the other possibility
is that it's because you did it by hand and not with
scissors, whatever, that it's not defined as an act of גיזה *geizah*.
Let's see how that, let's see now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
does and you'll see those ideas are still present in the ongoing
discussion. ותולש את השיער ובלבד שלא יזיזנו ממקומו *Vetolesh es hase'ar uvulvad
shelo yezizenu mimmekomo*. You can pull out the hair but you not
sort of remove it, meaning leave it sort of embedded in the
other wool of the sheep, I should say wool not hair, so
it doesn't look like you are shearing it. So because it's, so
it's more obvious what you're doing. אמר רב אשי אמר ריש לקיש
*Amar Rav Ashi Amar Reish Lakish*, לא no. שנו אלא Ella, ביד
*lo shanu ella beyad*. When do we allow all of this? This
is only if you use your hand. אבל בכלי אסור assur. *Aval
bikhli assur*, not if you use a vessel. Now that seems to
be because we're explaining the משנה *Mishnah* is not about intending something
else, but it's about defining it as not גיזה *geizah*, and they
feel if you're going to use any type of scissors or whatever,
then it's going to be defined as an act of גיזה *geizah*.
So only if you use your hands do we define it as
תלישה *telishah*, as pulling hair, pulling wool, rather than as shearing wool.
Any כלי *kli* specifically? Any כלי *kli*,
well I mean any כלי *kli* let's say with a blade. והתני
עושה מקום בקופיץ *Vehatani oseh makom bekupitz*, doesn't it say that you
clear away the way with a cleaver, which obviously פשט *pshat* means
you use this knife to cut away the hairs, and maybe again
you're not using, you're not using scissors, so it's not a classic
way of doing it, but you're still using this knife. So גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says תני *tani*, you should read לקופיץ *likupitz*. No, you
pluck away the hair so there's space for using a cleaver if
you want to actually for some bizarre reason שחט shecht *shecht* with
a cleaver. Okay, so once again we are seeing that there are,
that one way to read the משנה *Mishnah* is that it's about
the physical act being different, which is what allows it. It's plucking,
not shearing. Even that way you could have said that there are
some כלים *kelim* you can use that are also not classic, like
you could use a cleaver rather than a clipper, but they're saying
no, the משנה *Mishnah* is all about doing it in a way
that's כלאחר יד *kil'achar yad*, it's different, or it's not defined as
גיזה *geizah*, and it's only with your hand that it is enough,
it is different enough, as opposed to the other possibilities that we
just said about אינו מכוון *eino miskaven*. Okay, let's finish this up.
We really didn't, re-reading this משנה *Mishnah* these times.
Yeah, but on the other hand, it's a very nice גמרא *Gemara*
because it's playing with a lot of different conceptual categories, and it's
true the battleground of those different conceptual categories is the משנה *Mishnah*,
but there's no question, I would say פשט *pshat*, it's not so
clear that פשט *pshat* in the משנה *Mishnah* is אינו מכוון *eino
miskaven*. You could have totally said פשט *pshat* in the משנה *Mishnah*
is more like a שינוי shinui *shinui* and not being גיזה *geizah*,
but just read that the reason you're using a cleaver and not
clippers, it doesn't require your hand in order to do that, you
can do with anything that's not sort of a clippers, scraping away
a little space is not defined as an act of גיזה *geizah*.
Okay, so now אמר רב *Amar Rav*, ובלבד שלא יזיז *uvulvad shelo
yazi*, where do we, where are we?
Okay, וכן תולש את השיער Tolesh et ha-se'ar. לראות מום mum *vekhen
tolesh es hase'ar liros mum*. You can pull out some wool in
order to check for a blemish, whether it's a real blemish. איבעיא
להו *Iba'ya lehu*, they asked, לכתחילה lechatchila או דיעבד *lechatchilah o di'avad*.
Do you read this as לכתחילה *lechatchilah* you can pull out hair
to check for the wound, or does it mean that if hair
got pulled out while you were checking for the wound, you were
just trying to move it out of the way, but if wool
pulled out while you were checking for the wound, בדיעבד b'diavad. *bedi'avad*,
then leave it embedded in the rest of the wool like we
said in the first case in the משנה *Mishnah*? So אמר רבי
ירמיה amar Rabbi Yirmiya, *Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah*, תא שמע *ta shema*, come
and hear, צמח המסתבך באוזן *tzemach hamisabbach baozen*, if you have wool
that is sort of entangled up in the ear and you want
to check the ear for a blemish, רבי יוסי בן המשולם *Rabbi
Yose ben HaMeshulam*, man is he getting a lot of air space
today, רבי יוסי בן המשולם אומר *Rabbi Yose ben HaMeshulam omer* says,
תולשו ומראה את מומו *tolesho umareh es mumo*, you can pluck out
the hair and shows the blemish to somebody to inspect it to
see if it's a real blemish. So שמע מינה לכתחילה shma mina
lechatchila, *shema mina lechatchilah*, you see you can do it לכתחילה *lechatchilah*,
שמע מינה shma mina *shema mina*, you see that. אמר רב מרי
*Amar Rav Mari*, אף אנן נמי תנינא *af anan nami tanina*, it's
also really implicit in the משנה *Mishnah*. It says וכן התולש את
השיער לראות מקום מום lir'ot mekom mum and similarly pulling out hair
to see the blemish. מאי וכן mai v'chen what does it mean
similarly? אילימא שלא יזיז את מקומו ilima shelo yaziz et mekomo all
it means is once you plucked it out don't remove it, leave
it embedded in the wool. השתא hashta then that's obvious. ומה שוחט
דשחיטתו מוכחת עליו v'ma shochet deshchitato mochachat alav when I שחט shecht.
it, so it's obvious why I am pulling out the wool because
it's obvious I'm trying to שחט. shecht And even in that case
where it's obvious why I was pulling out the wool, nevertheless לא
יזיזנו לראות מום, lo yazizenu lir'ot mum, לא יזיזנו, lo yazizenu, you
cannot, don't remove the wool because that looks bad even when it's
obvious why I plucked it. So לראות מקום מום mum when you're
just trying to inspect the blemish, people don't see why that you're
inspecting the blemish, let's say let's say it's decided that that wasn't
a blemish and then you're not gonna then you'll bring it as
a קרבן. So they don't understand the context of why you're removing
the wool, so there's much more reason to say leave the wool
embedded. So מיבעיא miba'aya that wouldn't have been a question, so you
wouldn't have to say that in the end if all it was
about was leaving the wool embedded. That would have been self-evident. אלא
לאו התולש ela lav hatolesh if it's saying that about talking about
the wool for a blemish, it means that לכתחילה you can remove
that wool when you have to check for a blemish. שמע
מינה לכתחילה, you see if it's talking about pulling it, you can
do it לכתחילה, שמע מינה that is a good proof. So we
have the idea of מראית עין marit ayin and its misinterpretation and
leaving the wool embedded, but we basically have the idea of intention
of removing pulling out the wool and again with two basic explanations.
One is that it's not defined as an act of גיזה because
you used your hand or maybe as a פשט-meaning of the משנה
used a cleaver but not the standard cleaver, but the גמרא's insistent
you used your hand. Or the other explanation is אינו מתכוין which
could mean the act was accidental, could mean it was intentional but
not for the desire for the sake of benefiting from the wool.
Yes.
To say it's accidental would be contradicting what we said תולש tolesh
means in the סיפא, seifa, right? If we're saying in the רישא
reisha is תולש tolesh doesn't mean oh לכתחילה you can be תולש
tolesh you know? You're right. You're right.
Well that's consistent, that's a good point. That's consistent with the end
approach of the גמרא which moves away from the אינו מתכוין. The
end approach of the גמרא is all about the שינוי and the
בדיעבד. So you're right, that's true about the last discussion as well.
Let's now look at the next משנה. שיער בכור בעל מום. se'ar
bechor ba'al mum. So now you have the wool of a בעל
מום ba'al mum sheep. Now I think Michael asked yesterday and I
don't know why I wasn't thinking when I answered you, but about
what's the story after you שחט shecht a בכור, bechor, what can
you do with the wool? So it's actually quite explicit that you
can use the wool once you שחט shecht it. You're not allowed
to shear it when it's alive, but once you שחט shecht it
you're allowed to use the wool. So now the question is going
to be what happens about if there's a confusion? Or you don't
want people to be confused. It's not a confusion, but you don't
want people to misinterpret wool that came off before, you know, it's
before שחיטה shechita. and after שחיטה. shechita So let's take a look.
So שיער בכור בעל מום שנשר, se'ar bechor ba'al mum shenashar, if
it fell off by itself. Fell off by itself it wasn't sheared.
It's really totally permissible. והניחו בחלון vehinicho bechalon and you put it
in the window, like that we would say you put it in
the cupboard, you put it aside. Okay. ואחר כך שחטו v'achar kach
shachato and then you שחט shecht it. Now why you're not using
it before you שחט shecht it is obvious, because before you שחט
shecht it you're not using it, people see you using it the
wool of this sheep which is a בכור, bechor, they're going to
think you sheared it. They won't realize it fell off by itself.
But after you שחט shecht, it, now I'm allowed to use the
wool that I'm going to shear. So maybe there's no problem of
using this wool that I put aside. Why? because I'm using the
wool that I שחט, shecht I shouldn't be concerned about misunderstandings. So
the גמרא says עקביא בן מהללאל מתיר. Akavya ben Mahalalel matir. It's
quite fascinating talking about names of תנאים, Tannaim, you know, some types
of פרקים prakim we find תנאים, Tannaim, some types of מסכתות masechtot
that they were much more focused on than in other מסכתות. masechtot.
Anyway עקביא בן מהללאל Akavya ben Mahalalel says no problem. Since now
you can use the wool from the actual שחיטה shechita animal, you
can use this wool that fell off. It wasn't sheared what עקביא
Akavya excuse me it wasn't sheared so you can use it and
now it's there's no confusion because you can anyway use the wool
of the dead of the שחיטה shechitah, animal. וחכמים אוסרים vachachamim osrim
and וחכמים vachachamim say it's forbidden. We're still concerned that it's going
to either look bad or, forgetting look bad, רש"י Rashi says if
you allow me to benefit from even under any circumstance from wool
that fell off, maybe I'm not going to rush to give my
בכור bechor to the כהן. kohen. I'm not because I'll say I'll
wait a little bit of time you know maybe some more wool
will fall off I'm enjoying having it around the house I don't
know. Anyway we don't want you having it hanging around because then
you'll come to shear it you'll come to work it, problems are
going to arise. That's as the וחכמים vachachamim it's a side reason.
Okay. דברי רבי יהודה divrei Rabbi Yehuda
that's a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda explains it today. אמר לו רבי
יוסי amar lo Rabbi Yossi said רבי יוסי to him לא בזה
התיר עקביא בן מהללאל. lo veze hitir Akavya ben Mahalalel. No, no,
no. That wasn't the case that עקביא בן מהללאל Akavya ben Mahalalel
allowed it. אלא ela. but here's what he allowed. שיער בעל מום
שנשר והניחו בחלון. se'ar ba'al mum shenashar vehinicho bechalon. So again the
hair fell off, אגב agav by the way talking about goats' hair
because because by sheep it's not שיער. se'ar. What did it use
the phrase before did it say צמר? tzemer? Before what did it
say? תולש את השיער. Okay, but maybe there was also talking, I
don't know. Anyway, okay. So anyway, maybe it was talking about goats,
who knows. Anyway, okay. If it fell off and
you put it away
in the cupboard, and after that it died, and you shechted it
but it died. וזה עקביא בן מהללאל מתיר וחכמים אוסרין. Ve-zeh Akavia
ben Mahalalel matir ve-chachamim osrin. That's where they debate. Now as the
גמרא's going to say, but that's a case... well let's take... we'll
see what the גמרא says. Whether that's a case that's more obvious
it should be מותר muttar or more obvious it should be אסור.
assur. Now, צמר המדולדל, tzemer ha-meduldal, here it says the wools, so
maybe it doesn't... maybe we're talking about goats. Although no, if we're
talking about goat hair, you can't leave the goat hair intertwined, right?
I don't know. צמר המדולדל בבכור. tzemer ha-meduldal be-vchor. So let's say
you've got wool that has not totally fallen off. It's like it
fell off the skin but it's embedded in the rest of the
wool all by itself. Okay. Now until again, as it's been clear,
certainly until you shecht the animal, you can't use wool that has
fallen off. Once you shecht the animal, maybe yes, maybe no, that
was the debate. But your wool fell off but was embedded within
the wool of the animal itself, never fully fell off. את שנראה
עם הגיזה מותר ואת שאינו נראה עם הגיזה אסור. Et she-nireh im
ha-gizah muttar ve-et she-eino nireh im ha-gizah assur. Now I'm going to
shear it, right? It's almost exactly in time for next week's פרשה
parsha with Yehuda and the shearing of the sheep, or one פרשה
parsha off. Anyway, so the... if... if when I shear it, and
after it's sheared, it all looks the same, it all looks like
it was sheared, you know, sheared together, then I can use it
because... oh by the way, why am I shearing it? Sorry, it's
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Did it say that? It didn't say
בעל מום. ba'al mum. Okay, yeah, anyway, so it's a בעל מום
ba'al mum and then when...
one minute, hold on, I'm sorry, one minute, one minute.
If it's a בעל מום...
ba'al mum... right, it's a בעל מום, ba'al mum, I shecht it
and I shear it after I shecht it. Okay? That's what I
go... that's the... you know, that's what I was sort of implicit
thing that I was going to do in the beginning of the
משנה. So now, if the wool that fell off and was embedded
looks like it's one unit together with the rest of the wool,
if people see me benefiting it, they're going to assume, right, that
it was wool that I sheared after the animal died. But if
it's like somehow sticking out, right, and it's clear that it was
something that had fallen off already and gotten embedded, and that's clear
even after I shear it, then it's going to be clear that
I am benefiting from wool that fell off when the animal was
alive. And this is... and the חכמים, chachamim, as we've seen, as
opposed to עקביא בן מהללאל, Akavia ben Mahalalel, the חכמים chachamim do
not want me under any circumstance to benefit from wool that fell
off. So within the position of the חכמים chachamim that don't want
you to benefit from wool that fell off when it's alive, what
if it remained embedded and it was sheared after it was shechted?
Will that be enough to put it into the category of wool
that was sheared after it died? And that says it depends on
what it looks like.
Yeah, I just want to point out, if you don't mind me
saying this, that I think the reason you were saying before when
I was talking about the... and my question about this שיער בכור
בעל מום se'ar bechor ba'al mum about the חכמים, chachamim, it's not
as much that you're worried they won't give it to the כהן,
kohen, it's a בעל מום, ba'al mum, you don't give it to
a כהן kohen anyway. So you're saying that was the reason the
חכמים chachamim אסור. assur רש"י Rashi says, and I was thinking this
too, it's not because you're worried about giving... about delaying giving to
the כהן, kohen, but פסולי המוקדשין pesulei ha-mukdashin are still אסור assur.
בגיזה ועבודה. No, no, no, I said that.
So fine, fine, it's not about delaying giving it over, but it's
still about delaying shechting it. But the problem is, is that once
you can benefit from the... once you can benefit from the... the
wool or the hair that falls off, you're going to delay doing
what you need to do with it, which for a בעל מום,
ba'al mum, that means shecht it. And because of that, we're afraid
you're going to come to misuse. Okay, so let's take a look
now at the גמרא. So the גמרא says, מכלל דאסור. michlal de-assur.
So when... when רבי יוסי said... it's funny because it doesn't even
give you a framing of what we're going on. But when רבי
יוסי says, no, עקביא בן מהללאל Akavia ben Mahalalel didn't allow the
case about when it's shechted, he only allowed the case when it
died. And so what? The case when it's died is better? מכלל
דאסור? michlal de-assur? You mean when you shechted it, it would be
forbidden to benefit from the wool in that case? השתא במת שרי?
hashta be-meis shari?
If he allows when it dies... what happens by the way to
the animal, the בכור bechor that dies?
The בכור בעל מום. bechor ba'al mum.
You bury it, right? You can't get any הנאה, hana'ah, right? So
in that case, where... one minute... where the wool
that's attached... that's attached to the animal itself has to be buried
together with the animal, and he'll still allow the wool that fell
off when it was alive? So שחטה מבעיא? shachtah miba'i? When you
shechted it, there's any question? There you can benefit from the animal,
from the wool, of course he'll allow you to benefit from the
wool that fell off earlier. אלא, here's how you have to read
it. לא בזה התיר עקביא וחכמים אוסרין. Lo be-zeh hitir Akavia ve-chachamim
osrin.
Meaning when he said, no, that wasn't the case עקביא Akavia permitted,
he means that wasn't the case that was debated. That wasn't the
case where... the case of shechting it where עקביא Akavia said yes
and חכמים chachamim said no. Nobody was debating that case. They were
debating a more serious case of when the animal died and not
shechted. Okay.
שחטה, Shachtah, if you shechted it, דברי הכל שרי, divei hakol shari,
even the חכמים chachamim would say it's permissible. Once you can benefit
from the wool after שחיטה, you can benefit from the wool that
fell off earlier. כי פליגי, Ki pligi, when do they debate? במת,
be-meis, if it died. That's a much more difficult case. You
can't
benefit... Okay so that's a nice ואי *ve-i* but it's a very
logical ואי *ve-i* that he's saying. It's not, it's saying they didn't
argue this case, that case דברי הכל *divrei hakol* is okay, they
argued this more difficult case. אמר רב אסי Rav Assi... אמר ריש
לקיש *Amar Rav Assi amar Reish Lakish* מחלוקת בשהתירו מומחה mumche *machlokes
beshehitiru mumcha*, the case of can you now benefit from the wool
is that an expert and we're going to soon get into blemishes
and being inspected by experts an expert looked at it and said
yep it's okay it's a מום mum *mum* you can שחט shechts?
*shecht* it. מר סבר גזרינן דילמא אתי לשהוייה *Mar savar gazrinan dilma
ati lish-hu-ye* and here's what רש״י *Rashi* said before that why then
would there be a concern about benefiting from the wool that falls
off after the expert said it's fine it has a מום mum
*mum* so let me now use the wool that fell off? One
says no now we're afraid that you're going to say you're going
to keep holding it, you know, delaying שחט shechts *shechting* it and
so on so that you can benefit from the wool and that
will lead to misuse so that's גזרינן דילמא אתי לשהוייה *gazrinan dilma
ati lish-hu-ye* that you'll come to delay you'll come to postpone. ומר
סבר לא גזרינן *Umar savar lo gazrinan* the other one says we're
not making that safeguard it's not a big deal how much does
wool fall off anyway we're not concerned you can benefit from the
wool that falls off. אבל לא התירו מומחה *Aval lo hitiru mumcha*
let's say the expert did not say it was okay meaning that
then well let's see what it says לא התירו מומחה דברי הכל
אסור assur? *lo hitiru mumcha divrei hakol assur* everybody says that it
is forbidden. Why? Because when did the wool fall off? Did the
wool fall off after you were told that it was a בעל
מום ba'al mum. *baal mum* or before? So he says like this
if before you have something that looks like a blemish but you
don't have your הכשר *hechsher* you know from the expert that this
is a genuine blemish. So in that case in that case
it might not be a blemish and in that case the stakes
right are much higher because in that case you're not you know
until you get that okay you're not allowed to שחט shecht. *shecht*
it it might not be a blemish and it might be and
therefore there's a greater concern of misuse as opposed to a case
when you already know that it's a blemish you already got the
okay you can שחט shecht *shecht* it at any time and and
there there's less of a concern. Okay? Why?
I'm sorry it fell off anyway right?
But it falls after the expert said it's okay or not.
You used it you didn't use it you're only using it after
I know but wait a minute hold on let me just double
check רש״י *Rashi*.
Right
okay so רש״י *Rashi* is a little bit unclear I mean not
unclear he gives two reasons I would have maybe thought a third
about what why is there a greater concern when it does not
has not been looked at by the expert. רש״י *Rashi* says the
greater concern of why it hasn't been looked at by the expert
is the following if I don't know yet if it's a blemish
right so I have absolutely no incentive to hurry up with this.
Okay because it's quite possible it won't be a blemish and I'm
going to have to give it to a כהן kohen *Kohen*. So
if that's the possibility I'm going to take my sweet time okay
presumably and therefore there's a greater concern that I'll delay and therefore
there's a greater concern that I'll misuse.
Get more wool
misuse get more wool and therefore misuse. So before I was told
it was a blemish I have no urgency to do anything with
this and therefore there's a greater concern that's the first thing רש״י
*Rashi* says. The other thing רש״י *Rashi* says is that you know
before there's notice that it's a blemish then the whole thing is
going to the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. So therefore the whole sense of
it's okay because the hair fell off as I understand it's going
to be מותר muttar *mutar* in the end anyway you know that
would only be retroactive it wouldn't be at the time the hair
fell off so sort of in a formal way it's not framed
as permissible. I could have said yet a third thing which now
I forgot which I was thinking about when I was saying this
hold on what else could you say about why it's more of
a problem before it was ruled on because before it was ruled
on
no I'm not seeing that yet. Yes Charlie.
Well before the animal dies the wool is biblically prohibited right?
And this no no no that's not true if it has a
מום mum, *mum* and it's going to be permissible for my benefit
or whatever and I didn't שחט shechts *shecht* it then the wool
falls off then then it's okay. It doesn't become retroactively permitted it's
just a rabbinic problem of appearances of not to use the wool
you're saying this sounds like just purely דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*.
It is it is purely דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*. If I שחט shechted *shecht*
it it's a problem but if it fell off if it fell
off and it's a בעל מום baal mum, *baal mum* then it's
going to be okay since I didn't שחט shechted. *shecht* it. But
but if it fell off and it wasn't yet clear that it
was a בעל מום baal mum *baal mum* and that's the two
explanations רש״י *Rashi* gives. Number one is it's not clear so now
it's only retroactive I'm going to realize it was a בעל מום
baal mum *baal mum* or whatever but at the since at the
time I didn't it already has a much more problematic label associated
to it and number two is there's a likelihood that I will
postpone it even more. So that case when it has not fell
off before it got the הכשר *hechsher* of a מום mum *mum*
of the חכם chacham *Chacham* there it was more of a problem.
Yeah.
Interesting but I don't understand if you just make the גזירה *gezeira*
that says any wool that falls off can't be used until it's
shown to a
חכם *Chacham* or you know whatever an
expert right then what's the I don't understand what the problem is
you're not
going to
delay to
say because you can't use it
anyway.
Yes, and חז"ל Chazal understood that if we we don't have a
police going around making sure people are keeping to timetables. And they
understood that the way, it's sort of like the whole issue around
pollution where it's they often find it's more effective rather than to
have regulation but to have like tax credits and so on, right?
And then and that that makes sort of regulates people. So חז"ל
understand you want people to do something, you you focus on the
consequences. You're not you don't tell them oh you have to do
it by this time. Here are going to be consequences, okay? So,
yes.
Artscroll's framing of the whole case is it's already in the hands
of the כהן kohen's and the כהן's kohen. the one maybe delaying
bringing it to the בית המקדש.
That is true because the I'm sorry if I didn't make that
clear. You're right. I sort of spoke about you giving it to
the כהן. kohen's You know what? You're right. You're right. I for
some reason I appreciate that. For some reason I was thinking about
the case of a ספק safek where with the with the מום
mum you keep it. And in our case... Well, no, he can't
הלכתית halachically but not it doesn't he doesn't own it. But you're
right. It's not a גזילה gezeilah that you're stealing. Right, right. No,
but I you're right. I'm sorry. I apologize. I was conflating it
to the case of the of the ספק safek where you keep
it. But you're absolutely correct.
The כהן's kohen בכור bechor and the מום mum, only determines are
you bring it to the מזבח mizbeach. or not bringing it to
the מזבח.
Yes. So it's been given to the כהן kohen and now the
כהן kohen.
and then it falls off after the כהן. kohen. Yes. Thank you,
thank you. That was my mistake. So just then to restate that
just so it's very clear cut. It doesn't really change the substance
but just so we're clear about the case. So you've given the
בכור bechor to the כהן. kohen The question is does the כהן
kohen have to bring it as a קרבן or does he get
to שחט shechted it and eat it? Okay. The hair is falling
off. It got a מום mum and therefore the concerns are what?
So would the כהן is going to benefit from the hair once
he שחט? shocht If it has a מום mum. once he שחט
shocht he can shear it. But now he's not allowed to shear
it and use and use the wool. Okay. So the question is
and the hair fell off. So the concern is technically you can
but it doesn't look good. It looks like you might shear it.
You wait till you שחט. And the concern is is that if
we let you if do we want you to are we concerned
that he will wait around to get as much hair as possible
before he has to שחט it? Okay. And that is the concern.
And when there and therefore when it doesn't yet clearly have a
מום mum. the concern is maybe he has absolutely and now really
as you say he has absolutely no incentive to hurry up and
bring it as a קרבן because as a right and therefore well
no he gets the בשר. basar.
He gets to keep the skin.
Everything is more. All right. Well yes he gets the meat. Well
anyway he gets to also when he שחט anyway. But but at
the point is is that there he has anyway when he has
he's has less incentive to bring it as a קרבן. He's not
going to be as direct of a beneficiary and therefore we're more
concerned. Or again as way רש"י said it, since it does not
yet have a clear מום, mum you don't you know when the
wool falls off it's more questionable to begin with what its status
is. Okay. So that's the claim. That when it doesn't have a
מום mum. it's what do you call it? When it has a
מום mum but has not yet been checked. So let's keep on
going. We'll look at that we lost our entire lead. Okay. So
now the גמרא said okay
מתיב רב ששת. maseiv Rav Sheshes. So רב ששת Rav Sheshes asked
on this. בעלי מומים ba'alei mumim okay מתיב
רב ששת. maseiv Rav Sheshes. בעלי מומים אוסרין בכל שהוא. ba'alei mumim
osrin bechol shehu. If something has a מום, mum, a בכור bechor
has a מום mum and it gets mixed up with other sheep
then even you know one in a thousand it's all אסור. assur.
רבי יוסי אומר יבקר. Rabbi Yossi omer yivaker. Check it out. Let
him check it out. והוינן בה מאי יבקר? vehavinan bah mai yivaker?
What does that mean check it out? אילימא דבעל מום הוא ולישקליה.
eileima deba'al mum hu velishklei. If it means okay check out which
one had the blemish and remove it and the rest is okay.
מכלל דתנא קמא אמר לא? michlal detanna kamma amar lo? So the
תנא קמא tanna kamma would say that if you found the one
with the blemish you can't fix the problem? I mean what's they
talking about? So it must be that somehow you can't identify the
blemish and it was a very subtle blemish or who knows what
the case is. But since you can't identify it they're all problem-
meaning none of them can be brought as a קרבן. So אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה הכא בגיזת בכור בעל מום עסקינן.
amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha hacha begizas bechor ba'al mum
askinan. We're talking about shearing not the בכורים bechorim themselves got mixed
up but their shearings got mixed up. Okay. So what was the
case? שנתערבו בגיזי חולין. shenisarvu begizei chullin. It got mixed up with
shearings of חולין. chullin. Now what why so ומאן תנא קמא? uman
tanna kamma? And who is the תנא קמא? tanna kamma? רבי יהודה
היא דאמר נשחטו אסרו רבנן. Rabbi Yehuda hi de'amar nishchetu asru rabbanan.
So remember what basically the case is this hair fell off okay
and then you שחט it and then the question is what's the
status of the hair? So right that's the case of our משנה.
Not it doesn't literally mean גיזה because you didn't shear it. Hair
fell off of a בעל מום. baal mum, Okay then the animal
שחט. Is the hair מותר or אסור? assur So according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the חכמים chachamim would say that that's אסור. assur.
That forbidden hair gets mixed up with other with other shearings of
total non-בכור bechor shearings and then everything is אסור assur? since that
hair was אסור. That's the first opinion. And רבי יוסי who's interestingly
the same רבי יוסי of our משנה says oh no the חכמים
chachamim and the עקביא Akavya agreed that when you שחט it the
hair was okay. They only disagreed which what happens when the animal
died. Right, so therefore according to him everything is fine because the
whole hair wasn't forbidden to begin with. Okay, so let's take a
look. מאן
תנא כרבי יהודה היא דאמר Man tana k'Rabbi Yehuda hi d'amar נשחטו
אסרי. nishchatu assri. ורבי יוסי לטעמיה, v'Rabbi Yosi l'taameh, Rabbi Yosi is
going according to his reasoning, דאמר נשחטו שרו. d'amar nishchatu sharu. If
it's שחטed, they everybody agreed it's okay. The only case that was
debated was when the animal dies. דתניא יבוקר. d'tanya yivakar. It should
be checked. Now what has to be checked? Since he says that
the hair was never forbidden, what does he mean check it out?
מאי יבוקר? mai yivakar? What does it mean check it out? לא,
now according to what you said before, it must mean here's what
you check out. אם מום קבוע אם מום עובר הוא. im mum
kavua im mum over hu. What you have to check out is
the hair fell off of this sheep, it got mixed up with
other wool. Does it make the other wool forbidden? Well there's a
solution: שחט the sheep, right? Then it's the בכור bechor of a
בעל מום, baal mum. hair of a בעל מום baal mum that
was that fell off and then you שחטת shachtet it and it'll
be okay. Ah but he says wait, wait, you have to check
the sheep, maybe it didn't really have a מום. mum. Maybe you
thought it was the hair of a בעל מום baal mum but
maybe it was a מום עובר, mum over, a transitory מום. mum,
And that's what he means check it out. It looks like it
should be okay if it really fell off of a בעל מום,
baal mum we can check it, שוחט shocht and solve the whole
problem. But you have to check it out and make sure it
really was a בעל מום. baal mum You have to check it
out before you שוחט. shocht. Right, exactly. So the Gemara says... Ah,
now why is that relevant? Because that means that until now it
hasn't been checked. So you see that when the hair fell off,
even if the מום mum had not yet been checked, it can
be okay if you check it out and find that it was
genuinely a מום. mum So that disproves the idea that it has
to have fallen off only after the מום mum has been checked.
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so Rava says: לא, לא. יבוקר אי
יתיר מומחה אין ואי לא לא. yivakar i yatir mumche in v'i
lo lo. No, what you check out is, you don't check out
the בכור, bechor, you check out and you find out, hey did
you have this animal checked by a מומחה already or not? So
it doesn't mean you look at the מום, mum? but you find
out whether the מום mum had been checked, inspected or not. And
that would be the way to read it. אלא. כי סליק רבין
אמר לשמעתא קמי דרבי ירמיה. ki salik Rabin amar l'shmata kamei d'Rabbi
Yirmiya. When Rabin went up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said
this discussion to Rabbi Yirmiya. אמר רבי ירמיה, said in ארץ ישראל:
Eretz Yisrael: בבלאי טיפשאי, Bavla'ei tipsha'ei, stupid Babylonians, משום דייתבי בארעא דחשוכא.
mishum d'yatvi b'ara d'chashocha. I know, they dwell in a dark land,
אמרי שמעתא דמחשכן. amri shmata d'machshchan. They say, you know, their discussions
are dark. Meaning what type of like silly explanation is that of
the debate? לא שמיע להו, lo shamia lehu, הא דאמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, ha d'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan, מחלוקת בשבדק ולא מצא. machloket b'shebadak v'lo matza. The case
was, now you know, here's the case. It says a בעל מום
mum. got mixed up and your explaining what happened is: the hair
that fell off of a בעל מום mum, got mixed up with
other hair and you're checking out to find out if a חכם
was מתיר. mattir. That is not פשט, that is not פשט in
what happens if a בעל מום mum? gets mixed up. So a
בעל מום mum? did get mixed up. So what does it mean
check it out? What could you check out? Here's a very... and
here it's really like a fascinating question. And here the question is
like this: דקמיפלגי בשבדק. d'kamifligi b'shebadak. You checked, you inspected the entire
flock and none of the animals had a מום. So there's one
of two explanations of what happened, right? What are one of those
explanations?
מום עובר. mum over.
It didn't have a מום, meaning what? Meaning you thought it was
a מום and it went away.
Okay, or the other... after three explanations... but the other was that
the animal wandered away. But let's say it can't wander away. So
it had a מום and it went away. Or the other explanation...
It never had a מום in the first place?
No, no, they all have מומים. mumim. No,
you didn't do a good enough job. Okay. So what do we
say if you check it and nothing had a מום? Do we
say, ah, clearly it never had a מום or it went away
or whatever, or do we say it's all אסור? Obviously if you
keep on checking and nothing and nothing happens, you're back to where
you started from.
Okay, so the Gemara says דקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי מאיר ורבנן. d'kamifligi b'plugta
d'Rabbi Meir v'Rabbanan. The debate of Rabbi Meir and the Rabbis.
דתנן אמר רבי מאיר: d'tnan amar Rabbi Meir: כל דבר שהיה בחזקת
טומאה, kol davar shehaya b'chezkat tumah, anything that was assumed to be
טמא, tamei, לעולם היא בטומאתה, l'olam hi b'tumatah, it remains טמא. tamei.
This is about a field that somewhere in the field there was
a קבר kever buried somewhere in the field, you don't know where.
So can you check the entire field? You dig the entire field
and you find no קברים. kevarim. So what's the story, okay or
not okay? So Rabbi Meir says anything that was assumed to be
טמא, tamei, it remains in טומאה tumah עד שיתוודע הטומאה, ad sheyitvada
ha'tumah, until you find that source, until you find the קבר kever
the entire field is טמא. tamei. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, חופר עד
שמגיע לסלע. chofer ad shemagia l'sela.
You dig until you get to rock. Obviously nothing is under the
rock. או בתולה o betula or to virgin soil. And if you
checked the entire field and you didn't find it, you're okay. Even
though you knew there was a קבר kever before. I don't know
what happened, but I know it isn't here right now. So that's
the debate. רב אסי... so that's a very nice explanation. You checked,
you didn't find, do we trust those results or not? רב אסי
אמר רבי יוחנן, Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, מחלוקת בשבדק ומצא. machloket
b'shebadak u'matza.
This is even a more interesting question. You checked and you did
find an animal with a מום. But there's still a question.
Is it the same animal?
Is it a different animal? Right? וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי ורבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. v'kamifligi b'plugta d'Rabbi v'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. דתניא שדה שאבד בה
קבר. d'tanya sadeh she'avad bah kever.
There is a field that there is a קבר. kever. somewhere there,
you don't know where. הנכנס בתוכה טמא, Nichnas betochah tamei, anybody who
goes in the field is considered to be טמא, tamei, maybe you
walked over the grave. נמצא בתוכה קבר, Nimtza betochah kever,
now you found a grave in that field.
So a field that you didn't know was a grave?
No, you knew there was a grave, and you found a grave.
So הנכנס בתוכה טהור, Nichnas betochah tahor, now that that grave is
found and delineated, if you go in that field you're טהור tahor
as long as you don't walk over where we know the grave
is. שאני אומר הוא קבר שאבד הוא קבר שנמצא, Shani omer hu
kever she'avad hu kever shenimtza, the grave that was lost is the
grave that was found. דברי רבי, Divrei Rabbi,
that's what Rabbi says. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר יחפור את כל
השדה כולה, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer yachpor es kol hasadeh kulah,
I'm sorry, you can't assume what you found is the one. So
here it is, you looked, you found after checking five out of
a hundred sheep, one was a מום, you have to check the
other ninety-five sheep, or do you assume the one that you found
was the one that was a מום?
No, no, that's the other debate. Here the debate is, assuming if
you check the hundred you're okay, can you stop when you find
the one with a מום? Okay, and that's the debate. ורב אסי
מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבי חייא בר אבא, VeRav Assi mai ta'ama
lo amar keRabbi Chiyya bar Abba, why did Rav Assi not say
like Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, which is the case where you checked
and you didn't find anything? אמר לך, Amar lach, he would say
like this: בשלמא גבי טומאה, Bishlama gabei tumah, I understand by טומאה
tumah why they're debating, why it's possible you didn't find anything and
we say that it's טהור. tahor. אימר בא עורב ונטלה בא עכבר
ונטלה, Eimar ba oreiv unetalah ba achbar unetalah, maybe a raven or
a, you know, or some type of a weasel came and ate
away at the, assuming that the person was buried without a casket,
and basically just totally, you know, the stuff disintegrated and was eaten
away. So I can really believe that there's no grave here if
no grave was found, because if the grave that was here in
the past, you know, the weasels have eaten away at the body.
אלא הכא, Ela hacha, but here, how is it that you couldn't
find the blemish? במום להיכן אזל, Bemum leheichan azal, where did it
go? So I don't trust, I don't think you did a good
job if you didn't find it, I'm not going to מתיר matir
the flock. ואידך, Ve'idach, what would the other one say back? No,
אימר מום עובר היה, eimar mum over hayah, you guys figured that
out yourself, maybe it was a transitory blemish and it went away.
So if you didn't find it, I can assume it's not there.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'is eima, and it got better. Now, רבי חייא בר
אבא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבי אסי, Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba mai
ta'ama lo amar keRabbi Assi, why did Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba not
say like Rabbi Assi, the case where you found it and are
you allowed to stop looking or not? אמר לך, Amar lach, he'll
say to you: בשלמא שדה דרכה למקבר בה, Bishlama sadeh darchah lemikbar
bah, כי היכי דקבר בהאי קבר איניש אחרינא, ki heichi dekavar behai
kavar inish achrina, by a field, you bury people in a field.
So if there's one grave, it's quite possible there's another grave. You
can't stop just because you find one grave. אלא קדשים, Ela kodashim,
but by sacrifices, כיון דבדקינהו וקיימי, keivan debedkinhu vekaymi, the things that
you already pre-checked sacrifices for blemishes and that's why they're all here
as sanctified animals and sacrifices, they've been
pre-checked. ודרכיהו למיפל בהו מומא, Vedarchaihu lemipal behu muma, is it the
normal way that a blemish would occur? No. So if the animal
has a blemish, it's very unlikely it was another animal, it probably
is the same animal. ואידך, Ve'idach, and what would the other one
say back? אגב דמנכחי אהדדי, Agav deminkachi ahadadi, yeah, even after you
checked them, if you have a hundred animals together in a flock,
they're going to butt horns and they're going to, you know, rub
up against one another, שכיח בהו מומא, shachich behu muma, and it's
possible that there will be a blemish. So just because you found
one does not mean that it is the one that you lost.
Okay, with that we will end. The whole flock of קדשים. kodashim.
The whole flock of קדשים. kodashim.
In משנה we saw Rabbi יוחנן.
Yochanan.